When it comes to running in a competition, you may want to wear a wristwatch: you can time yourself, maybe check your breathing, just kind of keep things on a safe level.
You got to remember, when it comes to competition, you'll always want to keep going.
Even if it is a slow jog, a fast jog, something, just keep moving constantly.
Now when it comes to running in a competition, you might find that throughout your run you want to throw in a sprint, because when you throw in a sprint you got certain type of mobilizers within your body that are meant for sprinting.
It builds up those amino's, makes you faster, it is better overall.
After you throw in a sprint, just go to a slow jog to a fast jog go back down, but always keep running; don't stop.
So okay I run for this long this many hours, this many minutes, you go ahead and time your self put on a wrist watch or get someone to hold a stopwatch for you, but go ahead maybe put on some type of distance, and say I'm going to run this far and run that distance and know how well you do.
You can slowly expand on that, and if you are trying to do a specific kind of competition, go ahead and see what those requirements are for that competition, speed is, how fast people usually do things and how do they feel afterwards.
Just kind of what there strategies are and go ahead, and compare your results and their results.
If you find that your results are pretty good and you are like in a situation then, by all means go for the competition.
But, if you find your results are way negative and not even close to theirs, you may want to practice a little bit more before you decide to put yourself in that competition.